Guide to the Records of the New York Women's Anthropology Caucus MC.166
New York University Archives
Records of the New York Women's Anthropology Caucus
1972-2002
New York University Archives
New York Women's Anthropology Caucus
MC.166
3 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes and 1 flat box.
16 audiocassettes
16 sound discs (cd)
The Records of the New York Women's Anthropology Caucus document the founding and activities of a group of female anthropologists and anthropology students who were active in the New York City and international feminist movements. They were focused on women's rights and were an official non-governmental organization in the United Nations and were active from the 1970s to the 2000s. The records include meeting minutes, newsletters, correspondences, membership lists, funding proposals, scholarly papers, photographs, cassette tapes, and compact discs. Materials date from 1972 to 2002.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series:
NYWAC Records
IWAC Information, Correspondence, Publications
IWAC Conferences, Panels, Symposiums
Other Organizations
Audio (cassette tapes and compact dics) and Written Interview Material with NYWAC/IWAC members
Scope and Contents
The New York Women's Anthropology Conference and the International Women's Anthropology Conference records show the development of a feminist anthropologist organization from 1972 to 2002. The records document the organization's activities intended to bridge the gap between the academy and the international women's movement.
The records include meeting minutes, newsletters, correspondences, membership lists, funding proposals, scholarly papers, and photographs. The records also contain cassette tapes and compact discs of 14 oral history interviews and 3 written responses in which individual anthropologists recall what NYWAC and IWAC meant to them.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to Box 1, folders 17-18 is restricted. Materials contain sensitive student information.
The remainder of the collection is open without restrictions.
History of the New York Women's Anthropology Caucus
In 1972 the New York Women's Anthropology Caucus was formed by a group of women anthropologists who felt the need to examine critically anthropological writings from a feminist perspective, to encourage new research, and to identify and challenge the sexist academic practices that women students and professionals faced. Founding members were Eleanor Leacock, Ruby Rohrlich-Leavitt, and Constance Sutton. In November 1974 the group changed its name to the New York Women's Anthropology Conference (NYWAC) and became an official not-for-profit organization registered in the state of New York. At NYWAC meetings, held every second Friday during the academic year, women anthropology graduate students came together with more established women anthropologists to share their scholarly work and listen to a wide range of invited speakers. This group of about 25 to 40 women anthropologists meet originally at Columbia University's International House and then at the CUNY Graduate Center. NYWAC arose to fill the gap between intimate feminist anthropologist consciousness-raising groups, such as the Ruth Benedict Collective, and the more impersonal large-scale feminist associations that were emerging.
NYWAC served as both an educational forum and professional academic service for members. Meetings were devoted to discussing papers, courses, current ideas, employment opportunities, affirmative action, and the experience of women in the academy. It was an arena for disseminating anthropological information inflected with feminist concerns. Members addressed the critiques of feminist anthropologists concerning past anthropological writings and examined new feminist writings. A central aim of NYWAC from its first meeting forward was to offer an analysis from their distinct perspective as women. NYWAC worked to bridge the gap between activism and academia through their support of women workers who were on strike to demand better working conditions around New York. NYWAC crossed age and status lines in its membership which consisted of women anthropologists who held academic appointments, women working in "applied fields," and women graduate students.
NYWAC meetings were an important resource for younger scholars looking to navigate their way through the often biased world of the academy. Meeting agendas included discussions of the ethics of field research, the academic interview experience, and the ground-breaking courses NYWAC members were teaching on women. Together NYWAC members planned important panels on women and gender at the yearly American Anthropological Association meetings. In addition to being an important scholarly and professional network, NYWAC served as a social contact network to integrate professional and recreational activities through parties and informal gatherings.
Increasingly as the international aspects of the women's movement gained ascendancy and as more women anthropologists engaged in field research around the world, NYWAC turned its focus to the international arena. NYWAC renamed itself the International Women's Anthropology Conference (IWAC) in May 1976. In 1982 IWAC sought and achieved status as a Non-Governmental Organization (NGO) in consultative status with the United Nation's Economic and Social Council. Through this relationship it has had continued access to activities, conferences, and programs of the United Nations and has brought together an international network of anthropologists interested in research on women informed by a cross-cultural perspective. IWAC sought to influence international policies concerning women from its unique anthropological perspective. IWAC became involved in organizing activities related to the End of the Decade UN World Conference on Women held in Nairobi, Kenya, in 1985. This prompted members to publish the first issue of a series of fifteen newsletters to promote of an international exchange of data, research, and feminist perspectives among women anthropologist and those in related fields.
IWAC Newsletters spanned the years 1982 through 1995. Through the newsletter IWAC engaged in the exchange of information among its dispersed members concerning current research, women's projects, women's collective actions, and new publications. Issue number six of the IWAC Newsletter is devoted to reports on IWAC activities at the Forum '85 Nairobi Conference. A report on IWAC activities at the Beijing '95 Forum can be found in Voices, the Newsletter of the Association of Feminist Anthropologists of the American Anthropological Association. In addition, IWAC published two bulletins summarizing papers and discussions from their Wenner-Gren conference concerning a decade of women's collective action, 1975-1985, held in Mijas, Spain, in 1985, and from their panel on "Practicing Feminist Anthropology" organized for the International Interdisciplinary Conference on Women held in New York in 1990. Together with the Association for Feminist Anthropology, IWAC published two collections edited by Constance R. Sutton, From Labrador to Samoa: The Theory and Practice of Eleanor Burke Leacock (1993) and Feminism, Nationalism, and Militarism (1995).
IWAC's work in the international arena was diverse. IWAC members Mona Etienne and Eleanor Leacock brought together an international group of women anthropologists to write about the changes in women's roles and status following European colonization. They published 12 case studies in the book entitled Women and Colonization: Anthropological Perspectives (1980). IWAC members Leela Dube, Eleanor Leacock, and Shirley Ardener edited a collection of international contributions entitled Visibility and Power: Essays on Women in Society and Development (1986).
IWAC was led by an international Board of Directors composed of five officers and six members-at-large, each of the latter form a different country. At its height, IWAC claimed 500 members, half of whom were from Africa, Asia, the South Pacific, the Caribbean, and South America. The remaining members were from North America and Europe.
Members of IWAC's Board of Directors organized two Wenner-Gren Conferences. The first took place in August of 1980 at the Burg Wartenstein Conference Center, Austria. Organized by Eleanor Leacock and Helen Safa on the topic of "The Sexual Division of Labor, Development, and Women's Status," it marked the first all-women Wenner-Gren Conference with women scholars from around the world participating.
In November 1985, IWAC members Constance Sutton and Helen Safa organized a conference on "A Decade of Women's Collective Action: Anthropological Perspectives" in Mijas, Spain. This conference was also sponsored by the Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research. See IWAC Bulletin #1 for conference presentations and discussions.
Both NYWAC and IWAC were run on a voluntary basis with very limited financial support from the institutions to which various executive committee members were connected. However, the Wenner-Gren Foundation provided crucial financial support in enabling IWAC members to organize two international conferences, and small grants for various activities, such as funding to bring overseas women anthropologists to the IWAC organized panel "Practicing Feminist Anthropology: Views from Around the World," presented at the Fourth International Interdisciplinary Congress on Women (IICW) in 1990, and in the present archiving of NYWAC/IWAC records.
Highlights of IWAC's work in the international arena include the panels it organized at the NGO Forum in Nairobi, Kenya during the World Conference to Review and Appraise the Achievements of the UN Decade for Women in July 1985. IWAC's panels included: "Cross-cultural Perspectives on Women's Collective Actions"; "Women and Migration"; "Cross-cultural Perspectives on Women's Labor: Producing and Reproducing"; and "The Woman Question: Forward-Looking Research and Strategies," a brain-storming session. Ten years later at the NGO Forum in Beijing during the Fourth UN Conference on Women in 1995, IWAC also organized several panels.
Over the years, IWAC presented several well-attended panels at the annual meetings of the American Anthropological Association, and participated in a number of the preparatory conferences of Non-Governmental Organizations who were attempting to influence major UN documents, such as the Platform for Action that came out of the World Conference on Women in Beijing, China in 1995.
This collection indexes the ways that feminist anthropologists, both nationally and internationally, responded to issues raised by a globalizing women's movement. Along with the Ruth Benedict Collective, NYWAC and subsequently IWAC played a crucial role in creating an arena in which anthropological work could be examined from a feminist perspective. The materials exhibit the myriad ways in which many of the important debates of today have their roots in earlier discussions among feminist anthropologists involved in NYWAC and IWAC.
Source: NYWAC website
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance of this collection is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 02.016.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact university-archives@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2641, with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Women anthropologists.; Feminism.; Sutton, Constance R.; City University of New York; International Women's Anthropology Conference; Cole, Johnetta B.; Columbia University; Safa, Helen Icken; Leacock, Eleanor Burke, 1922-1987; United Nations; Rohrlich, Ruby
- Series I. NYWAC Records, 1972-1979; 184444
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes general information about NYWAC, meeting minutes, and correspondence.
  - NYWAC Mailing Lists and Meeting History, 1974; 184454 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - NYWAC Meeting Minutes, 1973-1976; 184455 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - NYWAC Minutes, 1974-1976; 184457 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NYWAC Minutes Copies, 1973-1976; 184456 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - NYWAC Correspondence, 1973-1979; 184458 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II. IWAC Information, Correspondence, Publications, 1976-2001; 184446
  The IWAC administrative series measures 10 linear inches and includes general information about NYWAC, membership forms, mailing lists, meeting minutes and notes, correspondences, IWAC interns at the UN, newsletters, and publications. This series contains primarily administrative documents, mailing lists, and correspondence. The series also contains IWAC's newsletters and two volumes edited by Constance Sutton and published by the Association for Feminist Anthropologists in collaboration with IWAC. IWAC's newsletters provide detailed accounts of IWAC's activities.
  - General Information about IWAC, 1976-1986; 184459 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Requests for IWAC Information, 1986-1995; 184460 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - IWAC Member Forms and Dues, 1985; 184461 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - IWAC Letters to Members, 1982-1995; 184462 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - IWAC Membership and Mailing Lists, 1985-1990; 184463 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - IWAC Minutes and Notes, 1986-1996; 184464 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Funding solicitation, 1987; 184465 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - IWAC Correspondence, 1982-2000; 184466 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence--Constance Sutton and Helen Callaway, 1986-1987; 184467 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - IWAC Correspondence Wenner-Gren, 1985-1987; 184468 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Archive and Oral History Correspondence with Wenner-Gren, 2001; 184469 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - IWAC Interns at the United Nations, 1995-1996; 184470 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access to folder 17 is restricted. Materials contain sensitive student information.
  - FInancial Records, 1986-1988; 188557 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Access to folder 18 is restricted. Materials contain sensitive student information.
  - IWAC Newsletters, 1982-1987; 184477 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - IWAC Newsletters, 1988-1995; 184478 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - From Labrador to Samoa, 1993; 184479 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Feminism, Nationalism, Militarism, 1995; 184480 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series III. IWAC Conferences, Panels, Symposium, 1985-2000; 184447
  Includes conference reports, papers given at conferences, correspondences concerning conferences, brochures, photographs, and notes.
  - Nairobi World Conference, 1985; 184481 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Nairobi Newspaper Forum, 1985; 184482 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mijas Conference, 1985; 184483 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Rapporteur Notes--Mijas Conference, 1985; 184484 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mijas Conference Correspondence, 1985-1986; 184485 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Book Project from Anthropological Perspectives, 1986; 184486 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mijas Conference, Revisions, Correspondence, 1988-1989; 184487 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mijas Papers, Revisions, Correspondence, 1985-1989; 184488 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mijas Papers, Revisions, Correspondence, 1987-1992; 184489 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Mijas Papers, Revisions, Correspondence, 1988-1993; 184490 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Third International Interdisciplinary Conference on Women, 1986-1987; 184491 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Plural Meanings of Feminism, 1987; 184492 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Practicing Feminist Anthropology, 1990; 184493 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Women's Caucus at PrepCom I and II, 1994; 184494 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Communicating Difference, Creating Unity, 1995; 184495 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Commission on Status of Women, Preparation for Beijing, 1993-1995; 184496 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - NGO Consultation in Preparation for Beijing, 1995; 184505 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - NGO Status and UN Participation, 1989-1994; 184506 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Preparation for Beijing Conference, 1994-1995; 184507 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Shaping the Future Symposium, 1995; 184508 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Post Beijing Information, 1995; 184509 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Post Beijing Women's Email Network, 1995-1996; 184510 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Post Beijing Women's Movement Email Network, 1996-1999; 184511 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Habitat II--UN Conference on Human Settlements, 1995-1999; 184512 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Beijing Plus Five Preparation and NGO Conference, 1999-2000; 184513 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Eleanor Leacock Award, 1987-1993; 184514 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Papers, CV, Correspondence for Leacock Award, 1993; 184515 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Papers, CVs, Correspondence for Leacock Award, 1993; 184516 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Leacock Collection, From Labrador to Samoa, Undated; 184517 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Dame Nita Barrow, 1987-1996; 184518 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Series IV. Other Organizations, 1980-2001; 184448
  Includes possible funding sources and related organizations' newsletters and publications.
  - Funding Sources, 1983-1987; 184519 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Event Announcements, 1993-2000; 184520 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Association for Feminist Anthropology Newsletters, 1985-1986; 184521 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Commission on Women-IUAES, 1989-1993; 184522 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - National Council for Research on Women, 1986; 184523 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Related Organization's Publications and Newsletters, 1983-1986; 184524 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Related Organization's Publications and Newsletters, 1986-1995; 184525 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Related Organization's Publications and Newsletters, 1995-1998; 184526 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Related Organizations Publications and Newsletters, 1998-2000; 184527 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Wenner-Gren Grant, 2001-2002; 184529 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series V. Audio (cassette tapes and compact dics) and Written Interview Material with NYWAC/IWAC members, 2001-2002; 184453; 16 audiocassettes; 16 sound discs (cd)
  Includes oral history interviews with Linda Basch, A. Lynn Bolles, Eva Friedlander, Angela Gilliam, Faye Harrison, Eve Hochwald, Gail Lerner, Johanna Lessinger, Susan Makiesky Barrow, Joan Mencher, Fran Rothstein, Helen Safa, Barbara Schroder, and Constance Sutton. Each interview is close to one hour long, with the exception of Constance Sutton's interview. There is written material from Christine Gailey, Donna Keren, June Nash, and a written addendum from Faye Harrison.
  - Written Interview Material and Misc., 2001-2002; 184528 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Interview with Angela Gilliam (audio cassette), 2001 November 30; cuid2156; 184530 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2156, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2156)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 59 min.
  - Intereview with Angela Gilliam (CD), 2001 November 30; 184544 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Eve Hochwald (audio cassette), 2001 November 21; cuid2157; 184531 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2157, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2157)
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 55 minutes
  - Interview with Eve Hochwald (CD), 2001 November 21; 184547 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Gail Lerner (audio cassette), 2001 December 28; cuid2158; 184532 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2158, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2158)
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 64 min.
  - Interview with Gail Lerner (CD), 2001 December 28; 184545 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Lynn Bolles (audio cassette), 2001 December 3; cuid2159; 184533 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2159, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2159)
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 47 min.
  - Interview with Lynn Bolles (CD), 2001 December 3; 184548 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Fran Rothstein (audio cassette), 2002 February 25; cuid2160; 184534 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2160, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2160)
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 52 min.
  - Interview with Fran Rothstein (CD), 2002 February 25; 184554 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Faye Harrison (audio cassette), 2001 December 2; cuid2161; 184535 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2161, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2161)
  - Interview with Faye Harrison (CD), 2001 December 2; 184546 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Barbara Schroder (audio cassette), 2001 December 19; cuid2162; 184536 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2162, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2162)
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 38 min.
  - Interview with Barbara Schroder (CD), 2001 December 19; 184555 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Helen Safa (audio cassette), 2001 November 26; cuid2163; 184537 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2163, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2163)
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 42 min.
  - Interview with Helen Safa (CD), 2001 November 26; 184549 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Helen Linda Basch (audio cassette), 2002 January 7; cuid2164; 184538 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2164, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2164)
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 61 min.
  - Interview with Helen Linda Basch (CD), 2002 January 7; 184550 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Susan Mariesky Barrow (CD), 2001 November 28; 184539 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Susan Mariesky Barrow (audio cassette), 2001 November 28; cuid2165; 184551 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2165, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2165)
  - Interview with Connie Sutton (audio cassette 1 of 3), 2002 March 2; cuid2166; 184540 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2166, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2166)
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 58 min.
  - Interview with Connie Sutton (audio cassette 2 of 3), 2002 March 2; cuid2170 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2170, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2170)
  - Interview with Connie Sutton (audio cassette 3 of 3), 2002 March 2; cuid2171 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2171, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2171)
  - Interview with Connie Sutton (3 CDs), 2001 November 21; 184558 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Eva Friedlander (audio cassette), 2002 May 2; cuid2167; 184541 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2167, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2167)
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 53 min.
  - Interview with Eva Friedlander (CD), 2002 May 2; 184557 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Joan Mencher (audio cassette), 2001 December 10; cuid2168; 184542 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2168, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2168)
    Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 63 min.
  - Interview with Joan Mencher (CD), 2001 December 10; 184556 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Hannah Lessinger (audio cassette), 2001 December 4; cuid2169; 184552 (Box 6, Cassette cuid2169, E-records nyuarchives_MC166, E-records cuid2169)
  - Interview with Hannah Lessinger (CD), 2001 December 4; 184553 (Box 6)